welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
welcome to the stoa i'm peter limberg
the steward of the stoa
and still has a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most
at the nice edge of this moment and
today
we have vince horn joining us
and i guess i'll i'll say how this sort
of came about
i was having a conversation with someone
recently and
they thought that the stoa was a really
good example of something
uh called the merasenga and he meant it
in more
and non-badus uh like buddhistic terms
sort of like a space that can house a
lot of
uh wisdom and spiritual traditions that
don't necessarily
talk or speak with one another and the
stoics are like a meta home for all this
and so i googled that term and then i
saw vince horn wrote an article about an
excellent article about it and it just
really landed
and so i reached out to vince like hey
do you want to come to talk about the
medicine guy he's like
yeah no but i want to talk about social
meditation
even better uh after reading some of the
content that he provided me about social
meditation
and so we uh set this session up and
how it's going to work i'm going to hand
it to vince in a moment
and it's going to be a mixture of kind
of a talk and
a practice session that being said i
will
take in vince
right thanks peter um everybody
good to see you um good to meet you
um my name is vince horn i'm i'm based
in
north carolina on the east coast of the
us
and i live in my home where i've been
for the last four months seemingly
without
without end i'm sure some of you can
relate
um but it's good to be here and that i
was excited to
to receive this invitation from peter
and i um i've been watching the stoa
since it
arose recently and participated i
participated in a couple sessions
including yesterday with um
bonita roy on her psychotechnology
playground so
i've been loving what's arising in this
community and thank you again for
for having me um yeah so so
um yeah i thought the meta song is a
really interesting idea but i thought
you know it would just end up being kind
of an abstract conversation about
meta-systematic
you know like community and i don't
really have a bunch to say about it
because i'm
to be honest still trying to figure out
how to actually
build these spaces and so i don't have
much to say on them because
it doesn't seem clear to me exactly how
to do that um but i think one of the
pieces that might be helpful or
one piece uh that i could imagine being
useful
in creating spaces where people are
practicing across
different traditional contexts is to
have
interpersonal practices available in
practices that we can do together
and of course social meditation is
nothing new
since people have been meditating which
is probably since people
since human beings were uh you know
we've been
we've been contemplating meditating
together
um you can look back at the history of
the kind of
indict traditions and see these
incredible examples of social
chanting you know of everyone chanting
over and over again out loud together
and getting into this deep sense of
collective flow
or trance and
i think it's really only been in the
last couple hundred years
uh with with with the advent of
modernity
that it seems like meditation has become
something new or different the way we
kind of currently understand it
and that is as a solo kind of
self-improvement project
you know meditation something we do to
improve ourselves or develop
our capacities or you know become better
at not reacting
to our you know impulses or uh you know
that
that's the kind of vision of modern
meditation uh everyone can be their own
authority
you know and everyone can can follow
their own path
and and i think there's something
beautiful about that but i
and i practice in that context um quite
a bit that's where i
began but i also found it quite also
limiting
to be focused primarily on my own
experience
all the time and so when i
first encountered uh the practice of
social meditation about 10 years ago
um from one of my own teachers
uh it was like a revel it was a bit of a
revelation um to me because i'd spent
about a year or so up to that point on
silent retreat
uh in my 20s i spent a year in total not
all at once
in silence meditating for 10 to 12 hours
a day
and that was a great experience except
that meditation and ex
it became this thing that like it was
only happening in my inner world and if
i could find some people who i could
talk to about it which were rare
um you know then we could have a sort of
esoteric conversation about our weird
mystical experiences
uh and and that was great but but it
felt like something that was very
isolated from
others from other people from the rest
of the world it felt like this thing
that just existed in my own mind
and so to do to actually verbalize and
to meditate out loud with another person
it just made me realize of course it
doesn't have to be that way
we could actually meditate together uh
again uh and and maybe we could do that
in
a new way we're not all just trying to
to to become
one with the same mantra you know what
what if instead there was a way to
acknowledge
the diversity of experience that can
arise
uh in in in our collective experiences
um and and and and yet not all just be
experiencing that diversity internally
while we sit together in silence
so for me social meditation is a
practice of bringing meditation
out of just one's inner experience and
into
a collective process of investigation
of
listening curiosity
so um so i'd like today to offer a
couple of social meditation
practices for for this group
with this group and these are very much
peer-to-peer
practices so if you if you find them
helpful and you want to share them
you can one because they're open source
and two because
uh you know anyone can facilitate these
these practices that the instructions
are quite simple
um uh actually uh
doing them is the challenging part
so uh today i wanted to offer a couple
examples
of social meditation practice and to do
the
do the practices together maybe like
five or ten minute
period of practice and then to open up
after each of these practices
and just check in and say hey you know
how was that for you what did you notice
uh were there any questions that came up
for you any insights that you had any
challenges
that occurred so there'll just be an
open space
for discussion after we do each
of these two techniques that's what i
like to propose
for our time today
um
the two techniques uh that i have in
mind one is um just a simple mindfulness
practice and it comes out of a technique
called social
noting and in noting meditation
traditionally this is a buddhist
practice
traditionally one would sit eyes closed
by oneself
and to internally note or label what's
arising moment to moment to give a
one or two word label um
to identify okay this is what's
happening right now
and in the practice of social noting the
only difference is we
do it out loud with other people
so that's the big that's the big
innovation
um and it's surprising surprisingly not
more people have thought of this
uh and yet when we do that my experience
after having done the noting
practice internally for i don't know 3
000 or so
hours i started to do it out loud and i
found wow this is a different practice
actually
it both is and isn't a different
practice it's different because
now i'm able to hear other people's
experience what
they're experiencing and not only that
i can model my experience
and and if you're able to meditate with
someone out loud
who has a few thousand hours of
experience under their belt
it's it's incredibly helpful to see
how they actually practice you know what
they actually experience
uh which is by the way no different than
what what each of us experiences
um and uh and and sometimes it's just
that it's just having someone
acknowledge oh there's anger
there's frustration there's a
self-aggrandizing thought
oh okay yeah just like me you know maybe
maybe i could
actually let this anger or let this
self-referential thinking maybe i could
actually notice that it's there and
and acknowledge that this is true for me
too
um and and i think that's the beauty of
social meditation
um you know we can we can see each
other's humanity
so the first practice i'd like to offer
is a it's a mindfulness-based practice
in which we will just moment-to-moment
uh be noticing what we're experiencing
and the form of that of this practice
is called there is noting
there is noting
this technique was developed by the
teacher that i mentioned earlier
uh kenneth falk who um had the bright
idea of doing these practices out loud
with other people
and the reason he did that actually was
pedagogical
he decided that the traditional method
of teaching
vapasana or mindfulness practice
this noting practice in particular
didn't work that well so traditionally
you'd go to
mostly you'd go to a monk uh and the
monk would give you the instructions
and then you go off and you practice the
instructions by yourself
and then at some point in the future
whether it's an hour or a day or a week
or month
or even longer you'd come back and
report
on your first person experience you say
okay when i did that
this is what happened and
then the monk would hear you you know
you
left for a lot of my teachers that
they'd be working with an asian monk
so then they'd have to deal with the
translation challenges between english
and
and um in this case bernice and
then the teacher would offer them
feedback and instructions okay do this
now
try this modify this and the problem
with that is there's so many different
places
in this in this way of learning
meditation where we can
um not understand each other where
there's some kind
of miscommunication and then there's
such a huge
long time between the initial receiving
of the instructions and getting feedback
on it
so the learning loop the feedback loop
of how quickly we can actually
understand put into practice and then
refine our technique
is extraordinarily long and what what
kenneth discovered is if you just do it
out loud with another person
and you just take turns for instance
going back and forth
noting out loud what you're experiencing
they're seeing there's thinking
there's dryness there is investigating
there's nervousness
there's allowing there's uncertainty
there's breathing
if you do that then very quickly
you can sort of see oh okay this is how
the practice works
oh okay got it ah okay
the thing that you just noted there um
that's that's more of a
of a thought than it is a sensation
right it's like
there is a fan moving above in the
ceiling it's like oh
actually no there's just they're seeing
you can actually make that more simple
so you can offer feedback and you kind
of very quickly refine the technique so
this
this practice arose as as as an attempt
to improve the pedagogy of teaching
meditation
and then the side effect is that it
becomes
interpersonal intersubjective
so in this practice the instructions are
we're gonna
we're gonna break out into small groups
of say three to four people each
and we're gonna have about 10 minutes to
just take turns
noting our experience as it's arising
saying there is and then using a word or
two
to describe what your current experience
is like
and this is your current sensory
experience you know what are you sensing
right now what are you seeing hearing
smelling tasting touching
feeling thinking feel free to use any
words you like that help describe
that experience in this practice
so there's a creative component to this
sometimes we call this freestyle noting
because
whatever you want to know is okay
whatever words you want to use to
describe your experience are fine
um and then the other important thing i
want to say about social meditation is
it's always
also okay to not participate in the
verbal
out loud component um because
as i'm sure some of you have experienced
you know social anxiety is a real thing
and sometimes it's not appropriate
perhaps to open up and share
our experience maybe we need to actually
um
you know ease our way into to that kind
of level of vulnerability
my wife often says trust is earned you
know so if you don't want to just come
blazing into just open sharing what
you're experiencing
you're also very welcome to participate
in this practice as a witness
so you can take the role of witness of
just silently observing
and participating through that silent
presence
so know that that's also an option in
this practice
and i'll probably ask if anyone wants
wants to do that beforehand so we can
just identify
and we can know who's witnessing so we
don't kind of expect each other
to be doing something we're not social
expectations
yeah a big part of social meditation
so let me stop here um are there any
questions so far
about uh the instructions uh or social
meditation
yeah uh is it like uh
you share one thing then they pass it to
the next person or you share for like a
minute just whatever is arising
yeah thank you for the question so when
it's your turn and we're going to sort
of take turns in this exercise
when it's your turn um you'll just say
there is
and then a word or two to describe your
current experience
and then then it'll be the next person's
turn so
if we were going to demonstrate this
safe uh peter if you and i we're gonna
demonstrate this
uh and we're gonna go back and forth and
maybe we can pull in travis as well
since
um they're going to be three or four
people so we could sort of demonstrate
what this will look like
uh with a small group would you would
you guys be up for that
yeah okay very cool
okay so we'll just do a few rounds here
so you can see what there is noting
looks like
there's sitting
there is hunger
there is touch
there is relaxing
there is thirst
there is hearing
there is breathing
there's sight
there is lightness
there is energy
there is opening
there is tingling
there is anticipating
there is performance
there's movement there is
gratitude thank you
so that's a perfect example of how this
practice works
thank you any other
questions uh sarah are there any
um recommendations for eyes open eyes
closed
um sitting standing um
uh in in in the context of these
instructions
uh that's not specified
so um it's up to you
uh any other questions
does anyone know that they'd like to
take the witnessing
stance during this exercise to check out
what it's like to be a silent observer
any witnesses
maybe the way i frame that made it sound
like if you're a witness that means you
can't handle intimacy it's not true you
can it's just a it's a cool way to
experience the practice as well
okay um great so so we'll all be
participating out loud part
and again we'll do this in the groups of
three to four and we'll have about 10
minutes
so we'll just break out you'll be in
your group someone will start to note
someone will go next and then after that
just like peter travis and i did and
then you've established an
order and you can just keep kind of
taking turns in that order
and again we'll come back here after 10
minutes and just check in
to see how it went
all right welcome back
looks like most everyone is still here
so i'm gonna
assume this was a successful practice
[Music]
um good job anyone want to share
anything about how that was for you or
anything any questions that came up
in doing the practice welcome kate
i'll just say it was flat out fun at
least you had fun
yes good to hear
thank you yeah i would like to add a uh
a
different energy of being pulled away
from distraction
due to the group's energy in a space
it's not like myself
whoops i forgot like that kind of wasn't
gonna happen because
there was some social pressure to stay
with that
um and that is a really interesting
different kind of flavor
really yeah great thank you benjamin so
so in a way i would really say what you
said like please uh
um no i think you said it beautifully i
would say like we we're just
we're distracted from our distractions
by other people's experience
there is uh sometimes
large upswellings of energy like
if one of us went out of turn or
if somebody said something that maybe
was funny or something
all of a sudden the energy would arise
and then it would settle down
and that was a fairly common occurrence
throughout the course of the 10 minutes
right awesome i'm a long time
student both in practice and
academically of
buddhism and so it was fun to see
oh my gosh here's impermanence last time
it was my turn i wasn't
noticing this i'm noticing something
else
and it's really basic but it was
entertaining and instructive
just to see things change things shift
thank you david there was something that
i noticed
or some it was compared to like some of
like
the solo meditation that i've been doing
i had to like
actively like hold myself back and like
let go of things because like every time
someone
said something you know like there is x
you know i just kind of wanted to be
like
you know like what makes you say that
where's that coming from like
like every single time i just wanted to
just like dive into it
but you know it wasn't my turn and i
couldn't even say that so i had to like
just
let it go which was really interesting
what kinds of things did you end up
noting frequently
there is letting go or um
usually around the time it got back to
me i would have been like
distracted by something else like um
my i've basically been in like a little
bit of like a fog for a while
so there's like you know like soreness
fatigue there
my back has just been terrible today so
there are lots of like physical stuff or
just sometimes
i think i said like i noted some
sensation
and i could sense like the various
reactions that had down the chain
you know i could just sort of like see
everyone's reaction was a reaction of
that which sort of like came back to me
and so when it came back to me i'm just
like yeah i feel pride you know like
that
it was it was interesting
thank you samuel um i just want to say
i came into the session with extreme
anxiety
i was feeling very on edge very
emotional
and now i have complete stillness i've
it's it's nullified everything
so it's just great
well glad to hear that um could have
gone the other way
but glad to hear that it's true for you
yeah thank you i'll go
um paul yeah at first it felt like we
were just sort of saying things
in my experience and then all of a
sudden i felt uh myself sinking into
like a bit of a wee space
and then it felt very like there were a
lot of things
that happened um i forget how someone
else said it but
things popping up distractions and it's
sort of
it felt like i was part of like some
sort of song or something there was like
a
rhythm to it there were different
qualities that were emerging which is
really nice
to be a part of nice thank you beautiful
description
i found it particularly impressive when
the sun
came out from behind the clouds the
light went up and it was
like my light went up too
my consciousness was going up
nice so the sun the sun brightened you
or maybe your whole group
nice that's great
anyone find this oh sorry go ahead
i found that i was
more like felt like i should give
context for other people but then also
like
maybe that's not the practice like if i
was doing this on my own i probably
would just say you know there is
smelling
and then what i'm saying to people i'm
like well they're going to want to know
what
it's maybe vegetables they're smelling
maybe cooking vegetables or something
yeah like because but that that seems
also like simply somehow but i noticed
that that
i i was doing that
um i mean it sounds to me like maybe
that's part of the social conditioning
you know that that we all uh carry um
like
smelling like that could be i could be
smelling my own farts right you know you
don't want
people to think you're you're over here
smelling your own
your own body odor so
so i mean that could be one reason to
want context
see makes sense but this practice
doesn't give you that
it doesn't afford that so instead we're
left
seeing car conditioning
yeah thank you
i seldom smell myself until i'm really
far down
smart going yeah good point yeah
it has to be pretty intense
fair enough
all right well um thank you all for for
trying this practice
um i wanted to to maybe do one more
practice
uh and have a chance to check in about
that
um so this next practice we did a sort
of mindfulness
practice to begin with and here i'd like
to offer
a heartfulness practice to kind of
incline the mind toward opening the
heart so
that's to me the practice of
heartfulness it doesn't mean we will
experience an open heart it just means
we're we're pointing uh
our intention uh the gps of our heart in
that direction
so um here uh the next practice
um this this practice is very simple
it's called spontaneous thanks
and in this practice the instructions
are in your small group
whenever you feel moved this is a
spontaneous part
feel free to say out loud thank you
that's it that's the practice
um are there any questions
everybody is saying thank you but
nothing else
uh yes uh when you feel moved as you
feel moved to say it
so this is kind of like a you could say
this is a gratitude practice
if you like it's focused on on
developing gratefulness
it's even a devotional practice if you
orient in that in that way
it can be
any other questions
in this practice you're also welcome to
witness whenever you whenever you want
because if you don't feel moved to say
thank you then you're witnessing um
so
thank you all right
we haven't done it yet but you're
welcome you're very welcome
um and and i'd say thank thanks to
ketamine also for this practice because
that's i was doing
some academy with some friends and this
practice
started just started happening and i was
like oh we could do that
too without drugs
not that i don't think it's fun to do
both
any other questions
okay so again we'll go for about 10
minutes in this practice
uh in small groups of three to four and
if you
don't feel moved at any time to say
thank you you're welcome to be silent
otherwise i hope you enjoy
all right thank you
welcome back so we've got
um just a few minutes here but if anyone
has anything you'd like to share
observations experience questions
please i i had this this moment of
intense social anxiety because
somebody sneezed and i just
spontaneously said oh bless you
and then i thought oh for anyone whose
eyes are closed that is gonna sound
really weird
so i sort of went off script and then
felt anxious about that
but it was of
a beautiful session thank you
yeah having been in that group with you
i i felt like it was a beautiful
off-script
moment from my point of view i was like
oh cool she's she's
she's modifying the instructions this is
good
this is how new that's how new forms
emerge in this practice right
now we have the bless you new forms come
from social
anxiety it's great
well it did fit for me for
there are different times where i felt
moved to verbalize and others
where anything that happened
a sneeze a blessing anything that
happened i was
thankful for and then there's sort of
um not to overstate it but generally
there wasn't a whole lot of me
anymore there was just thankfulness
everything that happened
thanked itself or was received
gratefully
thank you i'll sort of add to what david
said because that occurred at the
beginning and as
we sort of settled in with each other it
got quieter and quieter and quieter
there's less distinction
for me to be joy to be joyful or
thankful about it just got really really
quiet
um well
you know it came really easy to me
because i used to be in a zooming group
and that's what it was
all about
or the like emptiness and appearance
together
[Music]
a few things to share and then a
question
um one was i
i think i noticed for me that it was a
little bit more difficult
to access a thankfulness that would get
the threshold where i'd say thank you
when i had my eyes open versus eyes
closed
um i noticed that for me it felt
it was very quite distinctly like a
feeling
it kind of tended to like be somewhere
kind of between like my heart center and
like jaw area
and uh yeah i was wondering like
if you've ever experienced it where like
the thankfulness
that people express gets to like a point
of kind of like like hysterical
thankfulness like
like deep like oh my god thank you kind
of thing
yeah in some sessions i've seen that
yeah i had a a welling up of gratitude i
just wanted to like say thank you thank
you thank you thank you
and not stop um
[Music]
and the other thing i noticed was that
the the word think
uh just felt so weird like thank like
what is it what is that
um but it's also associated with that
that positive
that positive energy
there was a period of time where the
feeling moved started happening in a
continuous state
it was like flowing yeah and then i i
i r i i recognize that i have these
weird metacognitive structures because
it was like
oh now that it's flowing
do i feel moved or is it
like acceleration where you know you
only feel the change
and you know now now that it's just
flowing i don't know if i feel moved or
it's just moving
and i was like what does he mean by the
instruction
is it is it a continuous thank you thank
you thank you thank you thank you thank
you thank you thank you or is it
just the deceleration and acceleration
points that you say it
great question
um i think
in my room and in our room
i went from a state of uh happiness
to your humor to a hypnotic trance
and then to heartfeltness
keeping the h's keeping the h's going
that's good
beautiful thank you thank you for
sharing that um
and and i want to honor uh your time
so we could start to wrap here um
and thank you
peter back to you my friend
yes um so in a moment i guess i'll talk
about upcoming events but
thank you vince for coming today and
suggesting this um
excellent session and you also should
suggested that
it could be an ongoing session at like
uh at the store
and so it could be like a rotating
facilitator type thing too
maybe on a weekly or bi-weekly basis
because
i thought that was quite fun um so yeah
that's something maybe we'll throw in
the calendar of the wizard gym
um so for upcoming events
i don't even know what like i'm just my
mind's kind of uh
um what do we have tomorrow we have a
memetic mediator
campfire tomorrow so if you're
interested in memetic mediation
or you want to know what that even means
you can come to the session at 3 30 pm
eastern time
uh tomorrow and maybe uh aj if you want
to um
uh plug your shane boot camp um for next
week
yeah i do a shame boot camp every
thursday at six
and um coming up this coming thursday
we're just going to be
sharing some low-level shame stories and
practicing empathy with each other
so it's like a really nice um
give and take of vulnerability and
acceptance very cool i definitely
recommend checking that out
so yeah thank you everyone for coming up
today